# Hans Walter Behrens

Email: hw@behrens.cc Mobile: +1 310 347 7619

### SUMMARY

I am a fourth-year Ph.D. student and Dean's Fellow at Arizona State University. My research focus is on adversarially-resilient cooperative systems, especially in distributed ad hoc networks, as well as techniques for privacy preservation and decentralized autonomous decision-making.

#### EDUCATION

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Doctor of Philosophy, Computer Science (GPA: 4.12/4.00) Co-Advised by Profs. K. Selçuk Candan & Gail-Joon Ahn 2016 - 2021 (Expected)

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Master of Computer Science

2020

University of California, Irvine

Irvine, CA

Bachelor of Science, Information & Computer Science

2004 - 2007

# Refereed Publications

 Pando: Byzantine-Resistant Sensor Fusion through Hierarchical Overlay Ensembles HW Behrens and KS Candan

In Submission

- DataStorm: Coupled, Continuous Simulations for Complex Urban Environments HW Behrens, KS Candan, X Chen, Y Garg, ML Li, X Li, S Liu, ML Sapino In Submission
- WindRose: Adversarially-Resistant Oblivious Routing with Masked Geographic Targeting HW Behrens and KS Candan

In Submission

• Practical Security for Cooperative Ad Hoc Systems

HW Behrens and KS Candan

IEEE Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (**PerCom**) 2020 Forum Track

Velocity: Scalability Improvements in Block Propagation Through Rateless Erasure Coding<sup>1</sup>
 N Chawla, HW Behrens, D Tapp, D Boscovic, and KS Candan
 IEEE International Conference on Blockchain and Cryptocurrency (ICBC) 2019
 Research Track

 Load-Adaptive Continuous Coupled-Simulation Ensembles with DataStorm and Chameleon HW Behrens, ML Li, A Gadkari, Y Garg, X Chen, S Liu, and KS Candan Chameleon User Meeting (CHUM) 2019 Demonstration Track

• Adversarially-Resistant On-Demand Topic Channels for Wireless Sensor Networks

HW Behrens and KS Candan

IEEE International Symposium on Reliable Distributed Systems (SRDS) 2018 Research Track

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Finalist for Best Paper Award

- DataStorm-FE: A Data- and Decision-Flow and Coordination Engine for Coupled Simulation Ensembles HW Behrens, KS Candan, X Chen, A Gadkari, Y Garg, ML Li, et al.

  International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB) 2018

  Demonstration Track
- Lightweight Authentication of Fault-Tolerant Topic-Channel Queries in Distributed Systems HW Behrens and KS Candan

ACM International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC) 2018 Consortium Track

## SERVICE

- Conference Volunteer: (2017) CODASPY; (2018) HPDC; (2019) PLDI
- Publication Reviewer: (2017) ASONAM, TKDE; (2018) DASFAA, EDBT, EUROPAR, SIGKDD, TKDE; (2019) DASFAA, ICDE, TCC, TKDE
- Student Program Committee: (2019) S&P
- ASU Committees: University Hearing Board, Teaching Excellence Award Committee, Family Resources Advisory Board
- Graduate Student Mentorship Program: Designed, implemented, and ran a peer mentorship program pairing junior and senior graduate students within the department (≈300 PhD students) for academic, social, and professional support. Participants reported higher program satisfaction, improved mental health, and better team cohesion within and across research groups.

#### Professional Experience

# Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Dean's Fellow, Graduate Research Assistant, & Graduate Teaching Assistant

Aug 2016 - Present

- Awarded the prestigious Dean's Fellowship, a four-year paid fellowship reserved for the most promising Ph.D. students from each incoming class.
- Sole instructor for an introductory engineering course (ASU 101), responsible for curriculum design, lecture delivery, and grade evaluation of 130 undergraduate students.
- Designed and conducted a personal research agenda, under the Center for Assured and SCAlable Data Engineering (CASCADE), to explore novel ideas in the intersection of scalability and security.
- Successfully managed a team of graduate and undergraduate students in achieving our ambitious research goals, and leading to a successful top-tier publication of our complex distributed system.

# Canela Software, Inc.

Temecula, CA

Chief Technical Officer

Nov 2015 - Jul 2016

- Coordinated a major business pivot, requiring reallocation of approximately 85% of development resources. This pivot successfully produced a well-received prototype, and generated significant new client interest.
- Proposed, designed, and executed a complete overhaul of developmental process company-wide; proposals
  influenced release deployment, change management, issue tracking, code review, regression testing, and more.
- Organized a widespread shift to more well-defined agile methodologies, especially Scrum, to increase team flexibility to customer-driven changes; this flexibility proved a critical enabling factor for the success of our pivot.
- Principal Software Engineer

Jul 2011 - Nov 2015

- Designed and implemented enhancements to the software licensing system, enabling SaaS deployments, increasing enterprise penetration, and converting 5% of gross revenue to recurring revenue.
- Created an in-app store and purchasing system, increasing adoption of add-on products by 40%.
- $\circ$  Architected, designed, and rolled out a completely custom cloud database, opening up completely new markets and reducing cloud development overhead by almost 75%.
- Senior Software Engineer

- Built a new online software licensing system, reducing accounting workload by 4 hours per day, decreasing software piracy by over 95%, and increasing revenue by 14% year over year.
- Created an automatic update architecture to deploy incremental updates to over 10,000 client systems, reducing support requests by 12% and permitting the rapid release of new features.
- Software Engineer Jan 2008 Mar 2009
  - Designed a new calibration algorithm to increase rendering precision, which reduced measurement error below 0.01 mm and increased diagnosis accuracy by 4%.
  - Implemented a serial-to-USB interface for a new control method, increasing margins in regional markets by \$125/unit.
  - Added multi-monitor support to a diagnostic product, a feature which is now used by 10% of all installations.

### Honors & Awards

- Upsilon Pi Epsilon (ΥΠΕ), ACM Computing Honors Society, Founding President (Alpha Chapter of AZ).
- Phi Kappa Phi ( $\Phi K\Phi$ ), Graduate Honors Society, Member.
- Eta Kappa Nu (HKN), IEEE Honors Society, Member.
- Herbold Foundation Graduate Engineering Scholarship, (2019) for outstanding engineering graduate students.
- Achievement Rewards for College Scientists (ARCS) Foundation Scholar, (2019, Nominee) for scholastically outstanding doctoral students.
- Nora J. Folkenflik Memorial Essay Prize, for outstanding written communication.
- Chancellor's Achievement Scholarship, awarded to the top 0.1% of undergraduates.
- Travel Grant Awardee: (2019) NDSS, CHUM

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Primary Languages: Python, C++
- Automation: Ansible, OpenStack, Vagrant, Docker, Kubernetes
- Libraries: NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, NetworkX
- Others: Git, Linux, Unix, Ubuntu, Debian, CentOS, Bash, Zsh, LaTeX

## Relevant Coursework

- Applied Cryptography: Using cryptography to secure communication protocols over networked systems, including signatures, certificates, timestamps, elections, digital cash, and other multiparty coordination.
- Artificial Intelligence: Definitions of intelligence, computer problem solving, game playing, pattern recognition, theorem proving, and semantic information processing; evolutionary systems; heuristic programming.
- Bio-Inspired Computing: Discussing computational methods derived from biological processes and models including: evolution, immunology, social insects, metabolic scaling, and epidemiology.
- Cloud Computing: Virtualization, cloud computing, programmable networking, performance evaluation, information assurance, distributed and parallel computing, and cloud computing-based applications.
- Data Visualization: Covers techniques and algorithms for creating effective visualizations based on principles from graphic design, visual art, perceptual psychology and cognitive science to enhance the understanding of complex data.

- Distributed & Multiprocessor Operating Systems: Distributed systems architecture, remote file access, message-based systems, object-based systems, client/server paradigms, distributed algorithms, replication and consistency, and multiprocessor operating systems.
- **Distributed Database Systems:** Distributed database design, query processing, and transaction processing; distributed database architectures and interoperability; emerging technologies.
- Foundations of Algorithms: Advanced topics in formal algorithm design and analysis, including advanced shortest-paths algorithms, amortized analysis, network flows, NP-completeness, selected topics in computational geometry, as well as distributed, parallel, randomized, and approximation algorithms.
- Multimedia and Web Databases: Data models for high-dimensional and graph data; query processing and optimization for inexact retrieval; advanced indexing, clustering, and search techniques in high-dimensional spaces.
- Statistical Machine Learning: Spectral clustering, regression, classification, semi-supervised learning, feature reduction, manifold learning, ranking, kernel learning and multitask learning.